## MATTHEW PHILLIPS

matthew@matthewphillips.info

(859) - 489-0284

CONSULTANT / PRODUCT OWNER / ENGINEER / VUI

## **Profile**

I'm a consultant with a passion for products. My diverse experience allows me to fill in wherever you have needs. I have acted as a Product Owner, as a team lead on large projects, as an architect for the ecommerce web platforms, and have experience and speciality in IoT (Internet of Things) and voice user interfaces.

#### Skills

## **Product Owner**

I've lead projects such as large ecommerce sites that receive millions of page views per day.

## Debugging

Proficient in finding the root cause of bugs, performance deficiencies and memory leaks.

## Front-end

Experienced with progressive enhancement techniques to provide a base experience for all clients, and an enhanced experience for modern clients.

#### **Technical**

JavaScript	Node.js	Golang
React	TypeScript	С
Web components	Git	Zig

# Work experience

## Phillipsoft CEO / Consultant

2019-present

- Lead development teams in IoT projects such as smart kiosks and voice user interfaces.
- Developed a menu management system used by restaurants in dozens of the nation's largest airports.
- Worked on a kiosk project, developing a user interface and microcontroller integration, for a company with a
  presenence in retail markets throughout the U.S.
- Developed a voice skill for a calendar and agenda software company to give users information on historical and holiday related facts as a morning routine.
- Helped a company prototype an IoT interface for their home heating product. Designed a potential voice user interface for controlling the product.

## Bitovi

2013-present

#### Software Engineer

- Worked as a consultant on numerous projects and acted as the lead engineer on widely used open source projects CanJS, DoneJS, and StealJS. Worked for ~4 years exclusively on open-source and specialized in the lowest level web APIs.
- Lead team that rewrote mobile ecommerce application with millions of pageviews per day.
- Wrote performance review documents for several clients seeking help with poor performing applications (with React and general networking deficiencies).
- Developed expertise in streaming. Wrote <u>Velocirender</u> that took advantage of new technologies such as HTTP/2, W3C streams, typed arrays, etc. to speed up application boot time.

## J&L Marketing 2012-2013

## Lead Developer

- Worked as lead developer on rewriting the internal CMS / production system for a mid-sized marketing company. Wrote every line of code, including all C#, HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.
- Utilized reflexive design principles to achieve an interface that scaled from large desktops down to smartphones. Used Skeleton as the CSS framework, which gave us a 16 column grid system based on the 960 grid system.
- Used several HTML5 technologies on the project, including LocalStorage, Cache Manifest, CSS Transforms and Transitions and CORS.
- Consistently beat deadlines to ensure that the project will be delivered by the go-live date.

## Traffic Builders, Inc.

2011-2012

### **Programming Consultant**

- Rewrote the data import process to accommodate the large data loads their business endures (500k+ records import nightly, on one single-core server). The new import service sped up the process; testing large batches which normally took 65 minutes to process now import in ~7 minutes.
- Maintained their reporting web application, adding features as requested (http://www.revreports.com).
- Rewrote the service letter export process, stream-lining the code and building proper base classes, abstract classes, and interfaces where necessary. New code resulted in 30% faster processing.

Republic Bank 2010-2012

#### Programmer

- Designed application process for a debit card program. Interfaced with FIS web service APIs to transfer large sums of money across IP (tens of millions of dollars). Wrote Windows services to facilitate the transfer of money to customer accounts via flat files picked up by the bank.
- Worked with a web service to validate checks to be cut and sent to customers. Tightened the code resulting in an increase of performance by 150%.
- Designed and coded the new Release Check process, responsible for releasing all checks sent to customers as part of the bank's tax season business. This process is responsible for releasing billions of dollars to customers in only a few months. In the old, SQL based system releasing a large back of checks would take an hour and a half. In the newly designed process a batch of that size takes about five minutes.
- Worked with the OFAC system to screen for possible criminal customers using regular expressions.

## Traffic Builders, Inc.

2008-2010

#### **Application Systems Architect**

- Designed and developed a service reminder letter program, which included variable print data. This product
  led to an expansion in business due to the increased flexibility by having it in house. Developed Windows
  Services in C#, stored procedure for handling data in T-SQL, and created a user interface in ASP.net/C#.
- Developed reporting system to track client's marketing performance. Competing companies later developed a similar reporting product. Reports run on a schedule (program written in C#), running a series of stored procedures (T-SQL) to encapsulate data, then displayed in a Crystal Reports.
- Lead programming developer of the Results Exceleration & Verification (REV) automotive service marketing system. Developed a series of automotive targeted marketing products in C# (Windows Services, Console applications) and T-SQL. Created interfaces for internal customers in ASP.net.
- Upgraded data warehousing systems to accommodate new data sources, resulting in the savings of \$1,000+
  per month for the company. Wrote new procedures (C# and T-SQL) to handle the importation of CSV data
  files from a variety of sources into the production database.
- Developed a prediction algorithm for improved precision in one of the company's flagship products. The
  algorithm is written as a T-SQL function utilizing linear regression. A stored procedure handles running the
  function over many rows of data on a nightly basis.
- Maintained the performance of the REV database system. Used SQL Query Analyzer to optimize queries containing INSERTs of large quantities of data, resulting in 80+% performance improvements. Created maintenance plans (daily and weekly) to reorganize indexes and rebuild statistics on all tables (20+) in the database. Created traces using SQL Server Profiler to find troublesome queries that created bottlenecks on the server's performance.

## Kentucky Transportation Cabinet

2007-2008

#### Systems Administrator

 Served as primary liaison to IT for technical projects impacting Division of Right of Way and Utilities operations and processes. Facilitated communications with impacted stakeholders from interdisciplinary projects teams, utility companies, and road construction contractors. Teamed with developers to review use cases, source code, workflow process maps, and data models. Provided daily guidance for functionality, systems performance, adherence to user specifications, and acceptance testing. Developed custom tracking, monitoring, and reporting tools used to administer multiple, concurrent initiatives.

- Provided system administration expertise for development of Right of Way Management System (RWMS)
  project valued in excess of \$100,000. Helped QA code written in C# and ASP.net to ensure it met the project
  specifications.
- Developed suite of reporting tools using Crystal Reports, MS Access, and Web Intelligence that provided unprecedented levels of project tracking and monitoring capabilities.
- Enhanced real-time financial tracking capabilities by creating improved querying capabilities in MS Access
  database.
- Set standards for professionalism, interdisciplinary relationship management, and business workflow analysis
  as first team member to hold the role of Systems Analyst.

## **Education**

University of Kentucky - Lexington, Kentucky Bachelor of Arts, History

Matthew Phillips - matthew@matthewphillips.info - (859) - 489-0284